so in the previous discussion we
established that what the middle way is so the
that what the middle way is so the
question we should be asking ourselves
now is does that mean that whoever takes
on the Buddhist teaching let's say
converts to it from whatever other view
they were
following does that mean by that by
just have being convinced that the
Buddha is right and trying to do what he
says one should do why is already
practicing the middle
way
no what is
that because at the middle way depends
on having the noble right view it is
essentially the no full
path and this is something one needs to
acquire it is something one needs to see
directly for one
self um and that is frequently
um and that is frequently
overlooked nowadays so we cannot say
that everyone who genuinely considered
themselves to be practicing Buddhism are
therefore automatically practicing the
middle way um there is a further
discernment um is necessary for that so
what happens if a person thinks that I
know it's suffering is I know what
craving is I know what the sensation of
craving is and this practice that I'm
doing whatever it might be um is my way
to fortify that understanding that I
already have whether they cuz some
people might not take themselves to be
you know Noble ones but they feel that
they are kind of
yeah they have kind of this Middle
Ground where they can still access the
middle way whether it be the noble ail
path or any other practice even if they
don't specifically think of it that way
um which the Buddha said would lead to
the sensation of suffering
so um what is it
that how is it that a person can
know regardless of how how much they
might have improved their views
over period of time that that they still
don't have a middle
way well from the point of view of
ordinary person the noble disciple has
basically completely freed himself or
herself from
suffering that's got to be the
the basic view there so we're not
talking about sitting down regularly on
your meditation cushion and feeling a
bit more calm and peaceful on account of
that therefore suffering is diminishing
therefore I I conclude that I am
practicing the middle way or that I have
somewhere along the line uh along the
lines um acquired the the noble AAL path
it is um more fundamental than that so
one wants to be honest with
oneself and
recognize that you run a great Risk by
casually assuming that you are already
practicing the middle way whereas if you
put the bar as high as
possible you can still continue doing
what you're doing but you do not run the
risk of forming into the basic conceit
that you think you've got something
which infect you do not yeah so so
basically one way would be to say that
if the bar can be set higher it should
yes like there is nothing there is no
nothing to gain even in like a if you're
doing if you're going by by a wager
there's nothing to gain from setting the
bar Lower when you know that it could be
set higher so if you're practice of the
middle way leads you to be free from
suffering only sometimes or in certain
situations dependent on performing
certain things then you know that the
bar could be set set Higher by saying
well suffering should never arise in the
first place not that I should be having
a perfect um a perfect way for it to
kind of deal with it once it's already
there because
the one thing that's that should be
noted as well is that the no bful path
is not only
like you walk this path so as to be free
from suffering it is while you're
walking this path to the extent that
you're walking it you are free from
suffering so if you like basically Anar
hun is the one who perfectly walks the
no path all the time because it's not
like a destination it's just being on
that path means being free from
suffering MH to the extent you you have
understood it so it's not like a
momentary thing where I I do these eight
steps then I get freedom from suffering
then I repeat it again then I repeat it
again if that's the case then that's
just management um but apart from that let's
management um but apart from that let's
say uh like you said the person is doing
some kind of practice and they get a
little bit more peace out of it what if
they get a lot of Peace what if it
generally feels like you know everything
that they read in the sutas everything
that they kind of um makes sense to them
as as the what the Buddha
taught what if that that practice that
you're doing is generally seems to be
leading to that Direction like they
don't experience any
suffering um they feel like they know
the way
out um and there doesn't seem to be any
issues so what else can a
so what else can a
person um have as a criteria to
see whether that is adequate or not
MH like internally not not well one
thing that could consider
is like if they are practicing methods
techniques things like this they could ask
things like this they could ask
themselves what if I stop doing
this if the
piece that they think they have
disappears then they should conclude
that that piece was a very conditional
one that it dependent on them basically
managing their suffering um and that is
not at all the piece that is the very
foundation of the noil
path so so it's basically the extent to
which the extent to which you don't have
because the middle way should not be
understood just as a as as we said in
the last talk just as a choice between
um two extreme like it's it's not even
two extremes it's two sides so to speak
so it's not like if I just can avoid the
extremes I am walking the middle way uh
and and those those two sides are
obviously it's self it's called self
modification but in another suta the
Buddha talks about these two sides as
being Indulgence and those who
Indulgence and those who
regard observances as the
core so instead of talking it instead of
referring to it as self
mortification so if a
so if a
person if their practice depends on a
certain observance it doesn't matter
what it is it doesn't have to be like a
very of course rights and rituals which
is how
umasa is often conceived of it just
means if your practice depends on any
sort of action even if it's a mental
action of kind of going through these
mental drills of um be it breathing
techniques or even
contemplations if it is dependent on
that like if you can't stop doing it for
two years or more and still know without
a doubt that the same amount of freedom
is there that you had from the beginning
then you are regarding observances as
the core like your your your freedom is
dependent on those observances even if
it seems like they are diminishing your
suffering the fact that it depends on an
observance should already be seen as an
amount of suffering that hasn't been
overcome because as the Buddha said
being dependent on things is what
suffering is not like whether suffering
has arisen right now
so that is a form of and like it's it's
not accidental that it's synonymous with
self mortification because that's
another
thing self mortification doesn't have to
be on the level of mortifying the body
doesn't have to be on the level of um
making yourself experience physical
Sensations phys uh like it's just the
attitude of denial M
whereas whereby even thoughts that have Arisen
whereby even thoughts that have Arisen
things that have Arisen on their own as
a said these like the five Aggregates
have to be understood like it's a like
it's a pile of leaves that somebody
leaves out there in the in the forest
and like you obviously know that this is
not yours so if somebody's taking it
away or doing whatever they want with it
mhm um you should not be affected by it
so practices that revolve around
manipulating your your present
experience like I have this certain
feeling or this certain thinking and and
I need to get rid of it well for
AJ the identification with the five
Aggregates is always necessarily there
so they are essentially mortifying
themselves because they like the only
reason why they feel a need to get rid
of these feelings or get rid of these
thoughts is because they are identified
with them yes so it is self modification
in a very uh acute manner yeah so it
doesn't matter what piece comes out of
it the fact is if it was dependent on
this kind
of like control over the five Aggregates
means like basically yeah you have to abolish
like basically yeah you have to abolish
from the point of view of a PJ you
basically have to to to get rid of
yourself in order to reach that
peace whereas the the true middle way is
about abandoning abandoning the five
Aggregates as they
are so this should be we have you are
making a distinction between getting rid
of sense of self and abandoning agates
yeah so or you you don't have to regard
it as abandon abandoning sense of self
just uh sorry getting rid of sense of
self it's just as have said the badana
or assumption is not the same as the
five Aggregates no but there is
no uh there it's it's not that it's it's
not that it's the same it's not that
it's different rather it is a desire and
lust in regard to the five aggates that
is the bana there yes
so for as long as a person hasn't
understood what that upana is what that
assumption is MHM they only have two
options they either
indulge the
Aggregates like they try to make more of
the pleasure that they're already
experiencing they try to kind of
increase and PR proliferate further or
they try to change the Aggregates get
rid of them alter them in it so as to
make them different because the current
state is too unpleasant so I have to get
rid of it and both of these responses
are precisely the desire and lust
whiches to but it is still both of them
are still the desire and l so that's why
self mortification in this ultimate
sense is not different at all from from
Indulgence it's all of it is just rooted
in this attempted or this sense of
entitlement towards having the arrogance
different than the way they are so
now what is it
that I mean because again a person will
not be able to recognize what the
assumption is right away so they can't
use that criteria because they will be
telling themselves no I'm not trying to
get rid of the Aggregates they're going
to be sure of that or they might say I'm
just from now on going to accept
everything the way it arises exactly
which will then include all the wrong
views and habitual attitudes which are
part of the problem exact so to practice
a sort of let's say radical acceptance
or open awareness or or or or things
like that might on the surface um look like
that might on the surface um look like
it is very very close to the middle way
but actually it could be very far away
and it could be like you you would be
accepting the aggates again without
noticing because that's the thing you
don't have the criteria so you don't
have the criteria to see what is that
desire and lust so there is infinite
room for you to be still engaging with
it and seemingly um doing something
different yes because all you see is
kind of the the the obvious obvious
stuff uh so how then does go about it
how no not not just that before we get
into that how does somebody some a
criteria that a person even without
having discerned this acute assumption
how would they know that they are still
dependent on manipulating the
Aggregates apart from thinking in terms
of whether suffering can arise or not
because many people are assure that
their technique or they might not even
regard it as a technique but what
they're internally doing as a form of
management they're very sure that it's
going to work every time so there like
what would be another way for them to
know that there is still assumption
because assumption as well is there are
different types of assumption
uhhuh Assumption of
views Assumption of virtue and Duty
Assumption of sensuality and Assumption
of self yes so how would they
know indirectly so to say not based on
their own criteria because they can't
trust it but based on something else
that there is still an assumption
yeah so how is someone who is
still affected by upana who is still
assuming sense of self let's say as the
most fundamental upana how is someone
not going to deceive that it could be
you're including the the four
basic okay so these four kinds of
assumptions you just
mentioned how is someone going to be
honest with themselves as to whether
they are still assuming those
assumptions yeah without relying on
whether their practice seems to do the
trick or not
uhhuh well assum assumption and direct
knowledge don't they don't go together
one is only assuming because one doesn't
know and see for
oneself but then the difficulty still
emerges again because one might be
convincing oneself that it is otherwise
so there is a sort of it seems to me
you're asking about a basic kind of
self-deception that is going on yeah but
there there there would be ways for you
to kind of I mean it would require
honesty yes but things that would have
to be there anyway like even if as long
as there is assumption MH doesn't matter
how much your practice seems to work
these attitudes would still have to be
there these attitudes regarding your
practice would still have to be there
you would be passionate about your
practice B yeah so how would it would be
there to how would you measure that well
if you can stop
it and if you have an issue stopping it
then that's that's what he said as well that
that's that's what he said as well that
that's what we said ah now it occurs to
me like for example if someone questions
your views and your practices and you
feel the need to defense that what
you're doing is right you know that
you're still operating on the level of
assumptions exactly because there's a
suta I think it's ma 11 where the talks
about the he says whoever adheres to the
view of being which is kind of another
way of very generally describing this
attitude of accept accepting or
indulging uh they will argue with those
who adhere to the view of non-being
whoever aderes to the view of non-being
they will argue with those or they will
be against even if they don't explicitly
argue they will have
basically animosity towards those who
are arguing the view of being so for as
long as um for as long as you feel a need
as um for as long as you feel a need
exactly to defend that view it means
there is an assumption of views there
which would not be present in somebody
who has understood the nature of
assumption which is somebody who has
found the middle way
so that's a criteria that doesn't like
doesn't matter how it how much it works
for you if you still kind of
um not not that obviously I'm not saying
that you kind of abandon the recognition
that some things are right and some
things are wrong that's not what it
means it means emotionally if you feel a
need to defend what you regard as the
middle way then that's that's not the
middle way mhm because it should be like
it means you still doubt it it means
like the the statements of another
person are kind of internally shaking
you to the point where
you can't help but to try to justify why
this thing is right your your whole
sense of self or or let's say
personality view can be built up even
more with your religious or spiritual
practices making a whole identity out of
that somebody questioning those
practices and then you feel in the core
of your being challenged in what you
take yourself to be um that's a rather
Serious Sign that you're having the
whole thing backwards yeah because again
people might confuse uh supposedly not
clinging to any views which is another
view that you would be upset if like
when you when you hold to the view that
you shouldn't cling to any views you see
people clinging to the view to their
views and you get upset with them and
you start telling them off that's
because you're clinging to your view
right there yeah so
um but they they failed to see for
example the Buddha all the Buddha spent
time doing was saying this is right this
is wrong this is right this is wrong and
he was not clinging to to to his views
at all
so people need to look for it for deeper
criteria than just uh statements that
you make because clearly that that was
not the case like the Buddha did not
manifest his non- clinging through
making kind of open statements about
maybe other people are right I I'm not
the one I'm not the only one quite the
contrary yeah or for some people he he
he even said like whoever does not see
things in this way I say that they are
not a true renunciate yeah like he went
that far so that's not what clinging to
VI is
yeah so that so there is the view so
there are the views that are right and
that are wrong from the point of view of
Dharma factually that's one thing and
then how one let's say holds quote
unquote that internally that's another
thing yeah and so similarly there is the
observance of let's say precepts and in
a wider context there is virtue but how
how one is regarding that
internally that will be the factor that
determines whether somebody falls into
the Assumption of or the view
ofas or not you could you could about
the views you could basically say as
opposed to thinking that the right view
is another view that you take on like I
was following this other thing now I
just follow this one uhhuh uh it's more
like the right view is the understanding
of All Views because it's the it's the
overcoming of the Assumption of views M
so the right view is the view that
understands the nature of
views that's why it makes you kind of
incapable to to cling to it because it's
not a it's not on the same level as all
the other views it's not operating on
the same kind of I choose to believe
this as opposed to the other thing it's
like I understand what it is that would
make me uh believe in anything and I see that
me uh believe in anything and I see that
as not mine so to say I see that as as
not worth holding on to that's what the
right view is so um if others tried to
criticize that anything that others could be
that anything that others could be
criticizing would be a specific view not
the understanding of views yes like who
can criticize who can say that
understanding views is bad nobody can
say that so whatever they talk about by
necessity won't be the actual uh when
they're criticizing it won't be the
right view so if you again if you feel
offended that's because what is being
targeted is not the right View and
you're getting offended on account of it
means you're holding on to it to the
wrong view that EXA yeah well to any of
you like holding to to views is wrong in
of itself the Right View is not
something that you can hold on to that's
the difference yeah that's a
contradiction yeah yeah
so the um the same with the virtue like
it it's not that uh you
know when one overcomes attachment to
virt and practices one stop being stops
being virtuous it's more like because
the the as the Buddha said the the the
the actual practice The Virtue is seeing
the danger and the slight is fault it's
not on the level of precept specific
precepts you keep your specific precepts
so as to because as kind of guidelines
so there are certain things that can't
can never be done without them being
false but it shouldn't be like it it should
but it shouldn't be like it it should
you should come to the point where you
don't feel like being forced to not do
something being forced to give up one of
your practices
would feel like you're giving up the
dumo if it feels like that then that's
still something that you're holding on
to so the
the The Virtue as as we said in the last
talk The Virtue in practices is made
right not by what you're externally
doing because that's kind of Remains the
Same from puant just the case of monks
keep the patima uh keep the precepts
relay people and so on that doesn't
change it's internally the way of
relating to it so so that if you weren't
able to keep any of
this for x or y
reason you would
still not do anything UNH wholesome on
the on the level of intention exactly so
if you were to forget let's say if you
were to forget about everything you you
you learned you forget about the
precepts you don't know anything about
the dma
MH if there is real understanding
seeing the danger in the slightest fault
not engaging with UNH wholesome
Intentions by body and speech that would
remain so that's another way of testing
like am I holding on to Virtue and Duty
which means self modification
implicitly would be if I were to get you
know lose my memory completely if I just
get Alzheimer or something mhm will I do
I feel fear any kind of trepidation that
maybe this stuff that I've been
developing will will go I'll lose it MH
if that's the case
then it's it's it's like losing those
memories basically what what what else
is what else is it your practice is
dependent on these memories dependent on
these these things that could go
away just you head your head and and you
forget everything yeah that's just
content basically yeah so that that
exactly so it's a for as long as it's
that case for as long as it's like that
it's depending dependent on the
content and that's exactly what you
don't want as long as it's dependent on
the content it's not it's not
understanding MH as we said before if
it's a a particular view that you can
hold on to it can't be the understanding
of All
Views because the understanding of our
views is not a Content it's an
understanding of content yeah that's is
more backgrounds rather than or context
rather than contents yeah so it's it's
so so virtue should be uh a context a
context that's that then dictates your
actions but not because you feel like
you have to be doing specif these
specific actions but because the content
in itself is the
determinant or the context sorry the yes
the context in itself is the determinant
of what's right and what is wrong but
like ordinary person starts the other
way around yes they try to do the
particular stuff so as to reach the the
context so as to reach the kind of
wholesome and un wholesome which is
always on the level of the context yeah
so that's like inverting the order mhm
seeing that it should be the other way
around so you you can be you can be
doing the specific the same specific
actions but if the context is wrong then
doesn't matter how exactly to the letter
it is according to the precepts or
whatever it is wrong because the context
is wrong yeah and we have said earlier
that intentions behind one's actions
this is what we're now referring to as
context yeah yeah so those intentions as
well that's a that's also kind of where
the right the middle way would be
recognized as we were saying before if
your practice depends on if your
practice is based on recognizing your
intentions behind your actions and
then um
abandoning certain intentions that you
recognize are wrong that should if
you're truly doing that that should lead
you as opposed to
just kind of taking something on and
running with it like okay this is it and
I keep doing it y if you're really doing
that questioning your intentions behind
your actions you would you it would be
impossible for you not to recognize the craving the
for you not to recognize the craving the
assumptions the the emotional dependence
that is there on account of this
meditation practice or whatever that
you're doing
so and the the if your if your if your
practice is not revealing you those
things is not revealing
you why is it that you're doing this at
all how how how can you how can you
expect that it's going to reveal you
what read version delusion actually are
yeah so that has got to be the criteria
yeah yeah so this this okay I'm doing
this I'm doing that you can't argue on
the basis of the content because people
might read the sutas and say well no
this is exactly what I'm doing the Su
says this yeah so it is the the what
what kind of makes it at least closer to
be right or wrong is is this actually
revealing you these underlying
intentions that you have that you would
otherwise have been taking for granted
yeah because that's kind of um digging
digging ding with the knife as the
Buddha said as opposed to what people
usually assume that through a focusing
practice I'm delving closer into these
Sensations or something delving with a
knife is in the opposite direction yeah
it's delving into these so why am I
doing this where what are what is the
thing that's motivating this so that's
the kind of if you want to if you want
to hold on to
a certain virtue and practice like
that's that's
basically the the closest thing that if
you do it rightly it will be taking you
in the right direction at least because
that's the other thing you can't choose
not to hold on to it as long as you
don't have the right view so you have to
choose to hold on to the thing that's
least likely to be wrong yeah until that
disappears as well yeah so and and
during that uh Endeavor so to say you
have to be telling yourself no matter
how much sense it makes that there has
to be some way in which I am still
either indulging the aggates in the most
indulging the aggates in the most
General sense or denying them trying to
get rid of them because that that's what
kind of keeps you it keeps
you it forces you to keep refining it it
forces you to keep looking further MH
that's how you're uncovering these
intentions because it's a it's a
constant process of refinement very
which is basically an let's say a
thinking or pondering or considering
Right Here and Now based on one's
concrete situation so that cannot
actually be mechanical or habitual in
the sense that methods and techniques
usually are like regardless how I feel
um basically regardless of this concrete
situation I'm going to do my practice
which is for me all always the same that
is that is another way in which in in in
which you can see that it is that it is
not not going right you want to
precisely take into account this
concrete situation which is constituted
by feeling perception mood and all the
rest of it see what is going on there
and whether you're not either holding on
to something which is pleasurable there
or wanting to to change things on that
level yeah so in order to see that like
again everyone will start
out and it will it will be like a
novelty they will be able to see oh wow
I'm seeing my intentions now but if you
don't remember
that if you were to already see your
intentions truly or fully you would
already have the right view because you
would have seen by what craving is you
can you can even take that as watching
your intentions as your new virtue and
Duty that you cling to in a way that
you're not even trying to improve it so
to say you're just assuming okay this is
it and and just keep doing it so that's
why in the end it doesn't depend
on um like you know you might talk about
meditation techniques being you know the
obvious stuff like focusing
absorption uh breath observation or what
have you MH uh but that's not what makes
it wrong uh in and of itself like that
let's put it this way that is the very
coarse type of wrong but you can take
anything you can take again even this
that we're talking about now this
practice of watching your intentions
mhm in that same wrong way yeah so so
somebody could say I'm going to sit down
let's say or or or pause for a moment
what I'm doing what my intentions but
all of that could come out of reacting
to some unpleasant feeling which happens
to be there yeah and and that is that is
self modification in a way because you
are doing it because again this and
you're not questioning that you're kind
of focused on okay what am I going going
to do now I'm going to question my
intention like this blah blah blah blah
blah but behind that okay there's that
feeling and right then and there you're
trying to get rid of it so that is
that's kind of that's going against
yourself yes but mortification yes but
now suppose somebody recognizes that
right so they were affected by some
unpleasant feeling they've been
following what we are talking about just
now they say okay I pause for a minute
I'm going to check my intentions then
they recognize ahuh that's just
unpleasant feeling and sort of I was
just reacting to that by now taking on
this particular approach so they include
that then what is is there anything more
to be done than that or are we saying
that that is precisely what needs to be
recognized well if you do it fully
that's it but you won't be able to do it
once and then that's it no it is it is
not like oh now I've seen that I was
reacting to this doesn't feeling great
let's just carry on well that that's
what I said just now like again if
you're taking the middle way as uh kind
of a path that you walk once and boom
you arrive you arrive at a goal yeah but
no watching your intentions is the noble
a path that you walk always that's it
yeah so it's there's no end to it in the
sense like there is an end to it in the
sense that when you fully develop it
there is no room for suffering to arise
but it's not like
you kind
of okay that's it I I can forget about
my intentions now because I caught it
yeah it's it's more like okay you saw it
now but first and foremost you see
well precisely as the Buddha defined it
like an ordinary person is one who
doesn't even recognize their own mind so
you can't assume that because you
recognize it now
that in at any moment something else
might come up M so not like you start
searching for stuff but you certainly
don't rest in that recognition and then
you you you you kind of take it further
okay so look I have spent who knows how
many months practicing and I was
completely unaware of this it's I mean
or it's been happening many times and
only now I recognized it mhm what tells
me that there isn't
10 million other things like these
exactly in the same
principle that that right now just like
back then I was not aware of and now
like I'm I'm acting out of them still MH
so once you recognize that instead of
going in the kind of natural tendency of
okay I found it I found it you recognize
wait no this is this is just like
scraping surf the surface
so um you you would and then there's
there's like no there's no end to that
so say or at least you shouldn't be
anticipating an end to it because
recognizing your intentions in and of
itself is how you become safe like how
you prevent yourself from doing things
that are against your own
benefit mhm yeah one thing so so so what
you said earlier like one thing to
recognize an end is in a subtle sense
still wanting to get rid of things yeah
yeah because if you want if you want a
end to this yeah want to do yeah no like
you're still or you're still you're
still um yeah hoping for a reward at the
end yeah and like obviously yes there is
freedom from suffering there is nibana
there is all that but that doesn't have
that doesn't come on the level that you
expect that you can crave for because
whenever there is that kind of craving
and expectation that happens because of
an underlying intention that you're
ignoring yes so yeah so it's not going
to be your freedom from suffering it's
going to be freedom from suffering yeah
exactly so it is recognition of
recognition of intentions to the
necessary extent makes you unable to not
see that those intentions are not for
your benefit and then once every single
benefit and then once every single
intention of that kind has been
recognized you can't out of it act out
of it even if you want to because it
would have been obvious from the start
that this was not going to lead to any
harm it to any good uh it was only
because you didn't see it that you were
acting out of it so that's why the for
NOS go hand in hand you can't see this
is suffering without also seeing this is
the origin of suffering this is the
station of suffering and this is the way
the of suffering